Welcome to part 1 of our series on Recursive Language
Models. Despite valid context windows extending to millions of tokens,
frontier models like GPT-5 suffer from 'context rot,' where reasoning
capabilities degrade as input length increases. This topic explores why
simply increasing context size is insufficient for complex tasks and
introduces the motivation behind inference-time scaling.
In the world of artificial intelligence, we are witnessing an
explosion of memory. Modern language models can now technically ingest
entire libraries—millions of words—in a single prompt. It sounds like
the ultimate super-power: perfect recall at an infinite scale.
But there is a catch. Just because a model can swallow
a million words, doesn't mean it can digest them. As the
input grows, a phenomenon called 'Context Rot' sets in. The model's
attention gets diluted, drowning in the noise of its own memory.
It's not that the models simply forget. They can easily find a
specific password hidden in a book—that's the 'needle in a haystack' problem.
But ask them to track a complex plot or connect an idea
from page one to page five hundred? That's where they crumble.
This degradation isn't subtle. On tasks that require reasoning
across the whole text, performance doesn't just dip—it dives
off a cliff. The model's physical context window is
huge, but its effective reasoning window is surprisingly small.
Think of it like a computer. Trying to stuff
a million-token prompt into the model's active attention is
like trying to load a terabyte database entirely into
your RAM. It's inefficient, expensive, and frankly, overwhelming.
Computer science solved this decades ago with 'out-of-core' algorithms. If
a dataset is too big for memory, you don't crash.
You leave the data on the disk, and you fetch
only the chunks you need, when you need them.
This is the core idea behind 'Inference-Time Scaling.' Instead of
feeding the prompt into the neural network, we treat the
prompt as an external environment. The model uses code to
browse the text, read specific snippets, and reason iteratively.
The result? We stop the rot. By processing information in manageable
pieces, we can extend the reasoning capabilities of models by orders
of magnitude. It turns out the secret to reading a long
book isn't a bigger brain—it's learning how to turn the pages.
To recap: Physical context capacity does not equal effective
reasoning capacity; models suffer from 'context rot' as inputs
grow. The proposed solution shifts focus from architectural changes
to inference-time compute scaling. Next time, we will explore
Recursive Language Models (RLMs): The Core Architecture.